<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Uncategorized on StarksInfosec Research</title><link>https://starksinfosec.com/categories/uncategorized/</link><description>Recent content in Uncategorized on StarksInfosec Research</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><copyright>starksinfosec (CC BY 4.0)</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Apr 2023 11:44:55 +1000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://starksinfosec.com/categories/uncategorized/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>First Post Introduction</title><link>https://starksinfosec.com/blog/introduction/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Apr 2023 11:44:55 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://starksinfosec.com/blog/introduction/</guid><description>Introduction to Starksinfosec Blog I’ll share my research and insights on various security-related topics in this blog. I’ll cover everything from Threat Research, Vulnerability Research, Red and Blue Teaming, and some of the latest news on security.
My goal with this blog is to provide valuable information and resources to anyone interested in security, whether you’re just starting out or a seasoned pro. I’ll conduct research, share my experiences, and provide recommendations based on my findings.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction-to-starksinfosec-blog">Introduction to Starksinfosec Blog</h2>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
<p>I’ll share my research and insights on various security-related topics in this blog. I’ll cover everything from Threat Research, Vulnerability Research, Red and Blue Teaming, and some of the latest news on security.</p>
<p>My goal with this blog is to provide valuable information and resources to anyone interested in security, whether you’re just starting out or a seasoned pro. I’ll conduct research, share my experiences, and provide recommendations based on my findings.</p>
<p>So, if you’re ready to dive into the exciting world of infosec, then let’s get started!</p>
<p>This is my current plan and what I will post on this site this year.</p>
<ul>
<li>Slowly add changes to the site over time.</li>
<li>Post CTF writeups</li>
<li>Current ongoing projects ( Full enterprise home lab setup at home)</li>
<li>Home Server Upgrades</li>
<li>Research on info topics</li>
<li>Reversing Malware</li>
</ul>
<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>